Finding Aid for Mary Ellsworth papers, circa 1880-1983
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mary Ellsworth papers circa 1880-1983
Ellsworth, Mary
0.5 linear foot and 1 oversize folder (UAm)
9412 Aa 2; UAm
Naturalist and historian at the Nankin Mills Nature Center near Westland, Michigan. Nankin Mills was also used by Henry Ford in the manufacture of automobile parts. Nankin Mills files including notebook with research notes and jottings about the Nankin Mills area, newspaper clippings, and deeds; collected historical material including child's diary, 1902-1903, and Pontiac, Michigan family papers containing essay about women's suffrage, 1881; photographs of the Nankin Mills and related areas in western Wayne County, Michigan; copy prints of Pike's Peak, Colorado, 1887.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (donor no. 8051 ) was donated by John and Alice Ellsworth, brother and sister-in-law of Mary Ellsworth, September 1993.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Mary Ellsworth was a naturalist and historian at the Nankin Mills Nature Center in Westland, Michigan. After receiving her degree in Natural Science from Michigan State University in the mid-1950s, she worked for a time at the Cranbrook Institute of Science. In 1956, she was approached about a job to develop an interpretive nature center as part of the Middle Rouge Parkway in Wayne County. The location for the center was to be Nankin Mills, a site once occupied by two grist mills. The earliest of the mills was built between 1835 and 1842. A second mill was constructed soon after the Civil War. In 1918, Henry Ford purchased this mill as part of his plan to develop village mill industries along the Rouge River. After Henry Ford's death in 1947, the mill was given to the county and in 1956, the property was designated a nature center where school groups could learn about the area and take walks through the surrounding William P. Holliday Forest and Wildlife Preserve. The nature center was never adequately funded, and despite Ellsworth's best efforts, it closed in 1979 for budgetary reasons.
The Mary Ellsworth papers consist of two types of materials: 1) papers which relate specifically to Nankin Mills and to her work as naturalist, and 2) historical materials collected or received by Mary Ellsworth.
Subjects:
Teenage girls--Michigan--Diaries.; Diaries.; Ellsworth, Mary.; Nankin Mills (Mich.); Pontiac (Mich.); Women--Suffrage--United States.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ford Motor Company.; General stores--Michigan--Pikes Peak.; Mills--Michigan.; Nankin Mills (Mich.); Photographs.; Pikes Peak (Colo.)--1887.; Pikes Peak (Westland, Mich.)
- Nankin Mills Materials
  The Nankin Mills Materials sereis includes Ellsworth's personal notebook containing various types of information relating to the Nankin Mills Nature Center, including research notes, addresses of individuals, and various jottings. There are also newspaper clippings and other background information about the Mills, including copies of deeds to the property. Perhaps of greatest value are the photographs consisting of numerous images of the second mill, when it was a grist mill and when it was a manufacturer of parts for the Ford automobile, photos of nearby establishments in Pike's Peak, Michigan, as well as copy prints of views of Pike's Peak, Colorado in the 1880s.
  - Notebook containing research notes, addresses and various personal jottings of Mary Ellsworth (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1962-1983 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Deeds, 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - Historical information about the mills and the surrounding area (Box 1)
  - Photographs, ca. 1880-ca. 1950
    (see also oversize folder, UAm)
    - Nankin Mills views (Box 1)
    - Sites near Nankin Mills and related (Box 1)
    - Collected photos (include Pike's Peak, Colorado, 1887) (Box 1)
    - Negatives (Box 1)
- Collected Historical Materials
  TheCollected Historical Materials series includes materials Ellsworth collected. Although much of this material is of a miscellaneous character, there are still some items of interest. Of note is a diary of a young girl, Helen Fry, written around the turn of the century. Another folder consists of letters and essays written by members of the North family of Pontiac, Michigan in the 1880s. One of the essays relates to the topic of women's suffrage and was written in 1881.
  - Helen Fry diary (child's diary), 1902-1903 (Box 1)
  - North family papers, (Pontiac, Michigan family), circa 1881-circa 1890 (Box 1)
    (include essays and scattered correspondence; one essay concerns topic of women's suffrage, 1881)